<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gaming on Jonny Kates</title>
    <link>http://jonnykates.com/tags/gaming/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gaming on Jonny Kates</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://jonnykates.com/tags/gaming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Firewatch: My theories on this stunning game</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/firewatch-story-theories/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/firewatch-story-theories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Firewatch is a beautiful and immersive first-person &amp;lsquo;walking simulator&amp;rsquo; from independent game developers &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.camposanto.com/&#34;&gt;Campo Santo&lt;/a&gt;. It was recently published on Steam and I would extremely recommend playing it, or at least watching a playthrough of the game. It is a stunning game visually and truly unique from anything else I&amp;rsquo;ve played. It also has only about 5-7 hours gameplay; which is ideal for impatient gamers like myself who want a journey but aren&amp;rsquo;t interested in sinking 50 hours into a poorly paced RPG (I&amp;rsquo;m looking at you Fallout 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Players take on the role of Henry; who - for personal reasons - has volunteered as a fire watcher in the Shashone National Forest. The game hinges on the relationship between Henry and the only other character in the game, Delilah; a lookout at another tower. As the game progresses, the narrative meanders through dark themes of paranoia and vulnerability and an increasing sense of something being very wrong shrouds the player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the game ends, many of the questions surrounding the plot remain unanswered. Some people have been left very frustrated by this, but for me I found this to be one of the most interesting and intriguing aspects of Firewatch. I found myself thinking and hypothesising about the game for longer than it took me to actually complete it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, below are my theories on the game&amp;rsquo;s story arc; as posted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/Firewatch/comments/46s4pq/finished_today_heres_my_theory_of_the_main_story/&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delilah is a bit of a floozy and had a fling with Ned when he was on duty at Two Forks lookout. She shows the same behaviour with Henry; especially after drinking. She got along with Ned well enough to like him and allow him to let his son Brian stay at the tower and explore the park during his season there; but she was never in a proper relationship with Ned. If anything, she is more fond of spending time with the kid Brian than his dad.
At some point late in the season, Brian has a climbing accident whilst exploring alone and is killed. Ned instinctively searches for his missing son close to where he knows Brian has made a makeshift fort. Brian sometimes spends the whole night there, so Ned figures this is where he’ll be. After searching the area, he finds the body of his son in the cave and is devastated. He decides not to report the accident as it would put Delilah in serious trouble for knowingly allowing Brian to be in the park, at times unattended.
Instead Ned decides to tell Delilah that Brian returned to school and he too has had enough of the job and wants to leave his post, although he confesses that he doesn’t really have anywhere to go. Ned manipulates Delilah into letting him camp in the park. In return, he’ll run small errands for her like delivering her packages. Ned steals the keys to the cave and locks away the evidence of his son’s death - hoping that nobody has found the body in the interim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isolation and grief sends Ned down an unhealthy infatuation with Delilah. When Henry turns up, Ned feels jealous of the presumed ease at which Henry and Delilah can communicate through their 2-way radio. That level of access used to be privileged to him, but now he has to live in a hole in the ground; alone and unrequited. Who is this newbie? Ned loves Delilah and Henry is encroaching on what he sees as his.
Ned immediately resents Henry and wants to shake him up a bit. Being new to the stalking game, Ned is accidentally spotted by Henry on his very first evening, above the cave having just wrecked Two Peaks tower. Ned then steals some basic radio equipment from the nearby ecological station to begin monitoring the radio channel between H&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ned cuts the communications wire north of Two Peaks and frames the girls from the lake for the vandalism. This comms line is vital and so this really riles up Delilah, who asks Henry to then trash their camp. Henry seems reluctant initially over the radio, so Ned senses an opportunity to score points with Delilah. His hideout is closer to the girls’ camp than where Henry is, so he steams down there and trashes the campsite. The girls return, leave an angry note to Henry - whom they believe committed the act - and then leave. When Henry turns up at the campsite and tells Delilah he certainly didn’t do it, D knows deep down who did but she can’t come clean as she still harbours some level of loyalty to Ned. She’s also worried that if Henry finds Ned that she will get in trouble for allowing him to camp in the park.
Ned starts the ‘Flapjack’ fire (or whatever you named it in the game) in another attempt to spook and endanger Henry. He’s trying to ward him off of his beloved Delilah, but also he’s increasingly worried that Henry will find Brian’s body.
Delilah’s silence about Ned’s existence isn’t enough to stop Henry encountering Ned unexpectedly by the lake. Ned assaults Henry, but not before Henry is able to reveal to Delilah that someone has been listening to their conversations over the radio channel. D pretty much knows that this must be Ned but she doesn’t want to believe it. The seed of distrust for Ned is growing in her mind. She uses Henry as a pawn to investigate the issue further to get the proof she needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, Ned’s love for Delilah is turning sour. D’s chirpy ‘take a look at your trees poster’ message followed by the radio silence on the current channel isn’t exactly hard for Ned to work out. He simply searches the frequencies for their new channel. He feels betrayed.
He records D’s outburst about ‘burning the whole place to the ground’ and then uses Henry to relay this blackmail to D by planting the alarm clock backpack. When the alarm sounds, he knows exactly where Henry is so he knows he has time to climb the tower and pin the tape to the door. Ned gives Henry the key to the cave at this point because he is planning to murder him in cave. When Henry first visits the cave, Ned gets cold feet and tries once more to spook him by slamming the cage door. Ned is done: he can’t bring himself to kill Henry (perhaps in part because this would hurt D) so he records and plants a final recording for Henry, starts some more fires in rage, and flees.
Delilah is genuinely cut up by the news about Brian. She believes at worst that Ned murdered him and therefore she is culpable; or in the least that she is negligent by allowing Brian to be in the park in the first place. Delilah’s cowardice combined with the raging fires means she sees a way out of this without getting herself into hot water. She likes Henry but her fear of getting into trouble overrides this. She’s a screw up; an alcoholic; she has weak character. She can’t even face Henry due to her shame and guilt at the whole situation and just leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think by posting in that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/Firewatch/comments/46s4pq/finished_today_heres_my_theory_of_the_main_story/&#34;&gt;thread on Reddit&lt;/a&gt;. I go into a bit more detail about Wapati Station later on in the comments, so let me know!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve not played this game, then I encourage you to check it out or at least watch a playthrough and experience the story:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O_r6t6_bN3c&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://img.youtube.com/vi/O_r6t6_bN3c/0.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;IMAGE ALT TEXT HERE&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>