<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Politics on Jonny Kates</title>
    <link>http://jonnykates.com/tags/politics/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Politics on Jonny Kates</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://jonnykates.com/tags/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How the left can win</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/how-the-left-can-win/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2017 12:13:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/how-the-left-can-win/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, Theresa May has fired the starting gun this week on a snap general election in 7 weeks time. An election that she is determined to be focused on Brexit, with a core tenet of her platform being simply that destabalising the government at this point will jeapordise a successful Brexit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And whilst Brexit will clearly (and rightly) play an important factor in the vote, it&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that this is still a general election; not a rerun of last year&amp;rsquo;s referendum. The winner of which will have the responsibility of leading the &lt;em&gt;whole&lt;/em&gt; country over the next five years. Clearly that role is going to involve far more than just taking Britain out of the European Union; and actually that presents the left with a golden opportunity to put an end to this Tory government which is at risk of damaging our public services beyond repair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already, however, this feels like a very different election - not just because of the Brexit undertones and the surprise nature in which it was announced. Opinion polls seem to be predicting an irrevocable lead for the Conservatives; highlighting ongoing divisions amongst the Labour Party over its leadership and direction. Yet the opportunity for the left here is very real and I believe has been underestimated by the Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three things that need to happen over the next 7 weeks for the left to take advantage of this election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, Labour need to fully get behind Jeremy Corbyn&amp;rsquo;s campaign. Corbyn supporters have been saying as such since he was first elected to the leadership position, however that unity seems to have failed to materialise within the PLP let alone the wider supporter base. But with a general election round the corner, there simply isn&amp;rsquo;t time for the nay-sayers to derail Corbyn so it&amp;rsquo;s somewhat illogical to diminish his leadership over the next couple of months. Bury the hatchet and recognise that Labour is going to have to play a primary role in ousting this government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they can&amp;rsquo;t do it alone. Even the most skeptical poll critic has to acknowledge that it looks impossible that Labour could win a majority in a matter of weeks. Instead, the left needs to rally &lt;strong&gt;together&lt;/strong&gt; against the Tories as a means to an end. A progressive coalition is the best outcome for Labour, Lib Dems, Greens and the SNP. Collaborating on targeting winnable seats to avoid too many head-to-heads within the left could be vital - especially with the SNP&amp;rsquo;s role in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly the left-leaning amongst the electorate need to collaborate to tip the balance in our favour. Corbyn claimed this week that the political system is &amp;lsquo;rigged&amp;rsquo; in favour of those who protect and represent the elite. If the game is rigged, you have to cheat. Strategic voting amongst the left could again help to topple Tory seats. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen initiatives that help to organise tactical voting in the past, but it feels like this is going to have to play an integral role if we want a left coalition come June 8th. Gina Miller - the pro-EU campaigner who legally challenged the government over parliamentary voting for Article 50 - has set up a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gofundme.com/whats-best-for-britain&#34;&gt;crowdfunding campaign&lt;/a&gt; to finance candidates who specifically back an open vote on Brexit terms. Whilst this feels a little &amp;lsquo;single-policy&amp;rsquo; focused - which I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned I think we need to avoid - it&amp;rsquo;s an interesting initiative that highlights the need for taking on this election strategically.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The last days of Ceasar?</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/last-days-of-ceasar/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/last-days-of-ceasar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What a week. A week ago, the country was still digesting the game-changing news that Britain&amp;rsquo;s electorate had voted to leave the European Union. Since then, somewhere inbetween &amp;lsquo;the most things ever&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;not enough&amp;rsquo; has happened in UK politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course one of the things that &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have happened in the intervening week is that the Labour party should have rung the Tories out to dry. David Cameron used the promise/threat of an EU referendum to postpone his own party&amp;rsquo;s capitulation, only to have this backfire beyond repair at the expense of everyone in this country and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that&amp;rsquo;s not what happened. Instead, a large number of Labour MPs plotted - many weeks ago - to use this small window of opportunity whilst the belly of the beast was exposed to attempt a Caesar style assassination of their own leader. And so at this week&amp;rsquo;s PMQs, Jeremy Corbyn had to publicly tell off his &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; backbenchers whilst soon-to-be-retired Cameron, who is directly responsible for this mess, was able to point the finger at Corbyn and demand that he jump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve seen plenty within the left commentary columns and blogs this week that dismantle the Labour coup, but I&amp;rsquo;ve been surprised with the propensity that the mainstream media has propped up its legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regardless&lt;/strong&gt; of what you think of Corbyn&amp;rsquo;s politics or of the man as a leader; there are serious democratic questions to be asked of the PLP&amp;rsquo;s actions in the past week (and their behind-doors plotting months before that). Jeremy Corbyn won a &lt;em&gt;60%&lt;/em&gt; share of the membership vote only 9 months ago and since then, his standing amongst the membership has grown significantly. In the very same membership vote, Angela Eagle placed &lt;em&gt;fourth&lt;/em&gt; for the Deputy Leader position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, even if it were democratic, can we really conclude that Eagle is more electable than Corbyn? Does offering up Eagle as a &amp;lsquo;unity candidate&amp;rsquo; make any sense in the slightest? Well the answer ultimately depends on the question itself. What exactly, and according to whom, does democratic leadership of the Labour party look like right now? As far as I see it, the Labour party is being pulled - perhaps irrepressibly - in &lt;strong&gt;three&lt;/strong&gt; separate directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Labour membership voted for JC and has quietly broken membership growth records since his candidacy was announced. &lt;!-- Since Milliband introduced the £3-opt-in vote at the last count, the pool of people who were able to actually influence the direction of the party was widened significantly. Many feel this has been disastrous, yet for many (120k+); this was just the vehicle to finally allow someone who represented their personal politics to the fore. --&gt; This is legitimacy according to the gospel of the membership; and if Corbyn is on another ballot then he will inevitably be elected leader again. Corbyn&amp;rsquo;s continual membership support cannot be quashed by infighting. He will not resign. I am currently very anxious that this impasse will split the Labour party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you have the parliamentary Labour party, who appear more than anything to simply not like Jeremy Corbyn regardless of what the membership say. Now, this isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily a bad thing; although it flirts very, very, closely with the perminter of democracy and the media have been quick to prop it up. But what the PLP are currently saying is that after 9 months of trying as hard as they can, the people who work closely with Corbyn every single day simply don&amp;rsquo;t think that he has what it takes to win a general election. And as a Corbyn sympathiser, I am perfectly willing to listen and believe them. I had a lump in my throat when I watched &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/lgQjhj1BCY4?t=3m45s&#34;&gt;Angela&amp;rsquo;s tears and passion&lt;/a&gt; for Labour and have no doubt of her sincerity (if not her credentials). It is frankly not fair or right for the membership to dismiss the PLP&amp;rsquo;s concerns with such blind gusto as we have seen from some. Again, blindness from the other side of the fence will cause the Labour party to split.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then last but not least, you have the actual &lt;em&gt;labour&lt;/em&gt; whom the Labour party are supposed to represent at parliament; working class everyday-folk. This group are obviously numerically much larger and more important than the membership base and are the whole point of the Labour movement. Yet the public have been hugely forgotten in the furore. If we don&amp;rsquo;t win the General Election in 4+ years then we are not fulfilling our promise to the most vulnerable. And Labour certainly aren&amp;rsquo;t going to win whilst at civil war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really sad, but I cannot see a way out of this impasse that doesn&amp;rsquo;t result in an A.K.A. &amp;lsquo;Socialist Democrats Party&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;New Labour&amp;rsquo; split of the party. Yet whilst there&amp;rsquo;s still hope, both sides should listen to each other and think primarily of the movement.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My thoughts on the EU referendum</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/my-thoughts-on-the-eu-referendum/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/my-thoughts-on-the-eu-referendum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This referendum has tested my passion for politics. It has been crass, bitter and based on lies; mostly from the leave campaign. I don’t believe that there is one ‘right’ answer. There are valid arguments for both sides; and the debate would have been stronger if everyone had just admitted that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However there is one crutch that I think has propped up the leave campaign’s momentum from the start and that is the thin veil of immigration concerns, which I believe masks nothing short of xenophobia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A guy called Laurence Taylor echoed my feelings exactly with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://metro.co.uk/2016/06/22/who-is-laurence-taylor-guy-with-eu-referendum-ad-in-metro-explains-why-he-did-it-5959925/&#34;&gt;full-page ad&lt;/a&gt; that he took out in today’s Metro. “Why can’t we cope with a 0.5%/yr rise in population?” he writes; which is what 330,000 net from the EU comprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jonnykates.com/img/laurence-taylor-pie.png&#34; alt=&#34;Laurence Taylor&#39;s ad in today&#39;s Metro&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s raising two important issues here:
1. The ’76 million Turks’ scaremongering and Farage’s near-as-makes-no-difference fascist poster are inaccurate  and borne out of racism. Even with recent crises in population movements, anyone with any logic should throw these arguments out. However it feels like this is buoying most the leave share; which raises serious concerns about our society. I mean, someone actually got murdered over their vocal disregard for this xenophobic idiot herding whistle test.
2. If the concern is that more people means more stress on public services, then we have to look no further than a Conservative government that has slashed budgets despite existing growing pressures. Leaving the EU gives PM-elect BoJo and Michael FUCKING Gove another reason to choke departments and local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vote however you want. I think there are some valid reasons why Britain could benefit from leaving the EU. However it feels like many leave votes are propped up by my first point above, which makes me feel physically sick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a generation Y citizen of the world. I have no more or less in common with someone in Bucharest or Sunderland. Whether certain decisions are made by a stranger in Westminster or a stranger in Brussels is not as important to me as living in a society that isn’t divisive, insular and quick to forget the millions that died just 70 years ago for peace in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick PMQs</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/quick-pmqs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/quick-pmqs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One weekend recently, I built a small AngularJS project that offers short, Twitter-length summaries of the back-and-forth exchanges at the weekly Prime Minister&amp;rsquo;s Questions sessions in the House of Commons. I dubbed it &amp;lsquo;Quick PMQs&amp;rsquo;, and you can check it out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quickpmqs.co.uk&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise was mostly for my own benefit, so that I could get more familiar with Angular. But I do think that in someways it raises an interesting point. Debates in the House of Commons are often conducted over a backdrop of jeering, heckling and generally antagonistic behaviour. Also, the course of the debates themselves often descends into what can only be described as a personal slagging match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair to Jeremy Corbyn, the Labour leader has tried to reset the PMQ debate; not least by inviting the public to send him questions to be put to the Prime Minister. Despite his best interests, this has had limited success - as seen in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/cloakedtruth/videos/512311918942511/?pnref=story&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quickpmqs.co.uk&#34;&gt;Quick PMQs&lt;/a&gt; can offer a brief digest of the key points at the weekly debate between JC and David Cameron.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>