<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Jonny Kates</title>
    <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Jonny Kates</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 08:36:52 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://jonnykates.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Dropbox&#39;s 2017 rebrand</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/2017-10-05-dropbox-redesign/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 08:36:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/2017-10-05-dropbox-redesign/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, Dropbox shared their &lt;a href=&#34;http://dropbox.design&#34;&gt;new branding&lt;/a&gt; with the world; including a new logo, colour palette, illustration style, typography - essentially a complete overhaul of the Dropbox brand. The new identity takes the organisation in a wildly new direction and has caused &lt;a href=&#34;https://dribbble.com/shots/3849043-Dropbox-Rebrand&#34;&gt;quite a stir amongst the design community&lt;/a&gt;. You can take a look &lt;a href=&#34;http://dropbox.design&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dropbox have established themselves as a household name over more than a decade as one of the leading cloud file storage services. My mum uses Dropbox. So we have to ask &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; Dropbox felt the need to rebrand themselves in such an extreme manner at this stage in their development, with such an established and diverse user base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, the rebrand suggests that Dropbox wants to move away from being perceived as a business focused utility. But can a leopard change its spots? Shifting the identity in such an extreme matter isn&amp;rsquo;t going to change how users actually use the app. At it&amp;rsquo;s core, Dropbox &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a utility designed to do one fairly boring thing. The new brand doesn&amp;rsquo;t really sit well with the service&amp;rsquo;s purpose or user base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also what struck me yesterday whilst I was browsing through Dropbox&amp;rsquo;s big design reveal was how little I had previously touched any of Dropbox&amp;rsquo;s corporate identity in comparison to the amount that I actually use the service. I tend to just sync my Dropbox folders to my computers using the native file system, which obviously uses the core UI of the operating system. Very occasionally I find myself having to fetch a file from the cloud using the web app - usually from a folder that I don&amp;rsquo;t have selectively synced - which got me wondering how Dropbox are going to roll out this new identity into their web app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jonnykates.com/img/dropbox-web-app.png&#34; alt=&#34;My new Dropbox web app mockup&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jonnykates.com/img/dropbox-web-app.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Open full size image in a new tab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mockup may be a little crude, but if Dropbox push their new hugely experimental identity into what essentially is a file system then this is perhaps the sort of thing that my mum will be faced with when she next opens up Dropbox in her browser. Is that &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; necessary? Also, think again about the juxtaposition between the web app and the native Windows and Mac syncing app. Dropbox are departing from a clean, easy to use UI that matches somewhat the look and feel of an operating system&amp;rsquo;s file browser into an unexplored experimental UI that may make some users think there&amp;rsquo;s something wrong with their computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love the new logo glyph and I admire Dropbox&amp;rsquo;s bravery in this new approach but I can&amp;rsquo;t help think that it&amp;rsquo;s experimental for the sake of it and doesn&amp;rsquo;t reflect what Dropbox is as a service. Also, the colour scheme is too brutalistic to my eye for the sake of pushing boundaries and the typeface Sharp Grotesk is disgusting. It also comes with 259 fonts - so good luck establishing consistency across a huge organisation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How the left can win</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/how-the-left-can-win/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2017 12:13:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/how-the-left-can-win/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, Theresa May has fired the starting gun this week on a snap general election in 7 weeks time. An election that she is determined to be focused on Brexit, with a core tenet of her platform being simply that destabalising the government at this point will jeapordise a successful Brexit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And whilst Brexit will clearly (and rightly) play an important factor in the vote, it&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that this is still a general election; not a rerun of last year&amp;rsquo;s referendum. The winner of which will have the responsibility of leading the &lt;em&gt;whole&lt;/em&gt; country over the next five years. Clearly that role is going to involve far more than just taking Britain out of the European Union; and actually that presents the left with a golden opportunity to put an end to this Tory government which is at risk of damaging our public services beyond repair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already, however, this feels like a very different election - not just because of the Brexit undertones and the surprise nature in which it was announced. Opinion polls seem to be predicting an irrevocable lead for the Conservatives; highlighting ongoing divisions amongst the Labour Party over its leadership and direction. Yet the opportunity for the left here is very real and I believe has been underestimated by the Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three things that need to happen over the next 7 weeks for the left to take advantage of this election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, Labour need to fully get behind Jeremy Corbyn&amp;rsquo;s campaign. Corbyn supporters have been saying as such since he was first elected to the leadership position, however that unity seems to have failed to materialise within the PLP let alone the wider supporter base. But with a general election round the corner, there simply isn&amp;rsquo;t time for the nay-sayers to derail Corbyn so it&amp;rsquo;s somewhat illogical to diminish his leadership over the next couple of months. Bury the hatchet and recognise that Labour is going to have to play a primary role in ousting this government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they can&amp;rsquo;t do it alone. Even the most skeptical poll critic has to acknowledge that it looks impossible that Labour could win a majority in a matter of weeks. Instead, the left needs to rally &lt;strong&gt;together&lt;/strong&gt; against the Tories as a means to an end. A progressive coalition is the best outcome for Labour, Lib Dems, Greens and the SNP. Collaborating on targeting winnable seats to avoid too many head-to-heads within the left could be vital - especially with the SNP&amp;rsquo;s role in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly the left-leaning amongst the electorate need to collaborate to tip the balance in our favour. Corbyn claimed this week that the political system is &amp;lsquo;rigged&amp;rsquo; in favour of those who protect and represent the elite. If the game is rigged, you have to cheat. Strategic voting amongst the left could again help to topple Tory seats. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen initiatives that help to organise tactical voting in the past, but it feels like this is going to have to play an integral role if we want a left coalition come June 8th. Gina Miller - the pro-EU campaigner who legally challenged the government over parliamentary voting for Article 50 - has set up a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gofundme.com/whats-best-for-britain&#34;&gt;crowdfunding campaign&lt;/a&gt; to finance candidates who specifically back an open vote on Brexit terms. Whilst this feels a little &amp;lsquo;single-policy&amp;rsquo; focused - which I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned I think we need to avoid - it&amp;rsquo;s an interesting initiative that highlights the need for taking on this election strategically.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ch-ch-ch-ch-changes</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/ch-ch-ch-ch-changes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/ch-ch-ch-ch-changes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It feels like I&amp;rsquo;m on the cusp of a few major life changes. Next year, I&amp;rsquo;ll be getting married; moving house; and turning 30 - all possibly within a month of each other. In an attempt to minimise the risk of any potential mental breakdown, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to make some changes in my professional life today to put me in a better position to make these significant life changes (namely moving house) tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started working on a freelance basis as a designer and frontend developer for an organisation called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.raisingit.com/&#34;&gt;Raising IT&lt;/a&gt;. The work is mostly remote, meaning that Natalie and I can look at getting on the property ladder somewhere that isn&amp;rsquo;t the south east of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first became aware of Raising IT some years ago whilst working at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.clearlyso.com/&#34;&gt;ClearlySo&lt;/a&gt; and have followed their progress ever since. They have developed a website platform and CMS that is specifically tailored to the needs of non-profits. Features such as fundraising and social media integration are part of the platform out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where Raising IT really provide value though, is in the work they do with clients on their online strategy. Before any designs or any code is touched, clients complete a two day strategy workshop to hash out all of the many suggestions and ideas that are an inevitable part of any purpose driven organisation with numerous stakeholders. Before I sit with the client in a design capacity, these brainstorm discussions have already been tackled meaning that a lot of the heavy lifting in terms of defining the direction of the website have been nailed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who often works on projects from cover to cover in a project management capacity, this process is great from a designer&amp;rsquo;s perspective as it means the design process can be incredibly focused over a relatively short sprint. Two weeks in fact - from kicking off the design to having a fully signed off, built, and tested site template into which the client can populate their content. If you don&amp;rsquo;t distract designers from the design, they can produce results incredibly fast. Other efficiencies are baked into the development process as well - such as a starting SCSS framework that has been specifically tailored to Raising IT&amp;rsquo;s platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also great to be working with some clients who are doing incredible things; which is something I have missed in the past couple of years. I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to getting stuck into a new challenge and edging closer to full-time freelance work (if you hate your current website, hit me up!). Here&amp;rsquo;s to a busy 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The last days of Ceasar?</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/last-days-of-ceasar/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/last-days-of-ceasar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What a week. A week ago, the country was still digesting the game-changing news that Britain&amp;rsquo;s electorate had voted to leave the European Union. Since then, somewhere inbetween &amp;lsquo;the most things ever&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;not enough&amp;rsquo; has happened in UK politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course one of the things that &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have happened in the intervening week is that the Labour party should have rung the Tories out to dry. David Cameron used the promise/threat of an EU referendum to postpone his own party&amp;rsquo;s capitulation, only to have this backfire beyond repair at the expense of everyone in this country and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that&amp;rsquo;s not what happened. Instead, a large number of Labour MPs plotted - many weeks ago - to use this small window of opportunity whilst the belly of the beast was exposed to attempt a Caesar style assassination of their own leader. And so at this week&amp;rsquo;s PMQs, Jeremy Corbyn had to publicly tell off his &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; backbenchers whilst soon-to-be-retired Cameron, who is directly responsible for this mess, was able to point the finger at Corbyn and demand that he jump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve seen plenty within the left commentary columns and blogs this week that dismantle the Labour coup, but I&amp;rsquo;ve been surprised with the propensity that the mainstream media has propped up its legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regardless&lt;/strong&gt; of what you think of Corbyn&amp;rsquo;s politics or of the man as a leader; there are serious democratic questions to be asked of the PLP&amp;rsquo;s actions in the past week (and their behind-doors plotting months before that). Jeremy Corbyn won a &lt;em&gt;60%&lt;/em&gt; share of the membership vote only 9 months ago and since then, his standing amongst the membership has grown significantly. In the very same membership vote, Angela Eagle placed &lt;em&gt;fourth&lt;/em&gt; for the Deputy Leader position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, even if it were democratic, can we really conclude that Eagle is more electable than Corbyn? Does offering up Eagle as a &amp;lsquo;unity candidate&amp;rsquo; make any sense in the slightest? Well the answer ultimately depends on the question itself. What exactly, and according to whom, does democratic leadership of the Labour party look like right now? As far as I see it, the Labour party is being pulled - perhaps irrepressibly - in &lt;strong&gt;three&lt;/strong&gt; separate directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Labour membership voted for JC and has quietly broken membership growth records since his candidacy was announced. &lt;!-- Since Milliband introduced the £3-opt-in vote at the last count, the pool of people who were able to actually influence the direction of the party was widened significantly. Many feel this has been disastrous, yet for many (120k+); this was just the vehicle to finally allow someone who represented their personal politics to the fore. --&gt; This is legitimacy according to the gospel of the membership; and if Corbyn is on another ballot then he will inevitably be elected leader again. Corbyn&amp;rsquo;s continual membership support cannot be quashed by infighting. He will not resign. I am currently very anxious that this impasse will split the Labour party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you have the parliamentary Labour party, who appear more than anything to simply not like Jeremy Corbyn regardless of what the membership say. Now, this isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily a bad thing; although it flirts very, very, closely with the perminter of democracy and the media have been quick to prop it up. But what the PLP are currently saying is that after 9 months of trying as hard as they can, the people who work closely with Corbyn every single day simply don&amp;rsquo;t think that he has what it takes to win a general election. And as a Corbyn sympathiser, I am perfectly willing to listen and believe them. I had a lump in my throat when I watched &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/lgQjhj1BCY4?t=3m45s&#34;&gt;Angela&amp;rsquo;s tears and passion&lt;/a&gt; for Labour and have no doubt of her sincerity (if not her credentials). It is frankly not fair or right for the membership to dismiss the PLP&amp;rsquo;s concerns with such blind gusto as we have seen from some. Again, blindness from the other side of the fence will cause the Labour party to split.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then last but not least, you have the actual &lt;em&gt;labour&lt;/em&gt; whom the Labour party are supposed to represent at parliament; working class everyday-folk. This group are obviously numerically much larger and more important than the membership base and are the whole point of the Labour movement. Yet the public have been hugely forgotten in the furore. If we don&amp;rsquo;t win the General Election in 4+ years then we are not fulfilling our promise to the most vulnerable. And Labour certainly aren&amp;rsquo;t going to win whilst at civil war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really sad, but I cannot see a way out of this impasse that doesn&amp;rsquo;t result in an A.K.A. &amp;lsquo;Socialist Democrats Party&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;New Labour&amp;rsquo; split of the party. Yet whilst there&amp;rsquo;s still hope, both sides should listen to each other and think primarily of the movement.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My thoughts on the EU referendum</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/my-thoughts-on-the-eu-referendum/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/my-thoughts-on-the-eu-referendum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This referendum has tested my passion for politics. It has been crass, bitter and based on lies; mostly from the leave campaign. I don’t believe that there is one ‘right’ answer. There are valid arguments for both sides; and the debate would have been stronger if everyone had just admitted that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However there is one crutch that I think has propped up the leave campaign’s momentum from the start and that is the thin veil of immigration concerns, which I believe masks nothing short of xenophobia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A guy called Laurence Taylor echoed my feelings exactly with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://metro.co.uk/2016/06/22/who-is-laurence-taylor-guy-with-eu-referendum-ad-in-metro-explains-why-he-did-it-5959925/&#34;&gt;full-page ad&lt;/a&gt; that he took out in today’s Metro. “Why can’t we cope with a 0.5%/yr rise in population?” he writes; which is what 330,000 net from the EU comprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jonnykates.com/img/laurence-taylor-pie.png&#34; alt=&#34;Laurence Taylor&#39;s ad in today&#39;s Metro&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s raising two important issues here:
1. The ’76 million Turks’ scaremongering and Farage’s near-as-makes-no-difference fascist poster are inaccurate  and borne out of racism. Even with recent crises in population movements, anyone with any logic should throw these arguments out. However it feels like this is buoying most the leave share; which raises serious concerns about our society. I mean, someone actually got murdered over their vocal disregard for this xenophobic idiot herding whistle test.
2. If the concern is that more people means more stress on public services, then we have to look no further than a Conservative government that has slashed budgets despite existing growing pressures. Leaving the EU gives PM-elect BoJo and Michael FUCKING Gove another reason to choke departments and local government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vote however you want. I think there are some valid reasons why Britain could benefit from leaving the EU. However it feels like many leave votes are propped up by my first point above, which makes me feel physically sick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a generation Y citizen of the world. I have no more or less in common with someone in Bucharest or Sunderland. Whether certain decisions are made by a stranger in Westminster or a stranger in Brussels is not as important to me as living in a society that isn’t divisive, insular and quick to forget the millions that died just 70 years ago for peace in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lake Scene Illustration</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/lake-scene-illustration/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/lake-scene-illustration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jonnykates.com/img/iso-lake-scene.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jonnykates.com/img/iso-lake-scene.png&#34; alt=&#34;Lake scene&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a well needed break from work last week, and whilst I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to totally disconnect myself from technology, I did spend some valuable (and hot!) quiet time in rural Devon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like isometric technical drawings so I wanted to work on something that had this kind of perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Critter illustration</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/critter-illustration/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/critter-illustration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jonnykates.com/img/critter-illustration.png&#34; alt=&#34;Critter&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I drew this little chappy for a recent side project at work. The design was part of an overall branding brief for the project and we wanted to include a character in some of the more important illustrations around the site to give it some personality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was drawn entirely in Sketch.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Firewatch: My theories on this stunning game</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/firewatch-story-theories/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/firewatch-story-theories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Firewatch is a beautiful and immersive first-person &amp;lsquo;walking simulator&amp;rsquo; from independent game developers &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.camposanto.com/&#34;&gt;Campo Santo&lt;/a&gt;. It was recently published on Steam and I would extremely recommend playing it, or at least watching a playthrough of the game. It is a stunning game visually and truly unique from anything else I&amp;rsquo;ve played. It also has only about 5-7 hours gameplay; which is ideal for impatient gamers like myself who want a journey but aren&amp;rsquo;t interested in sinking 50 hours into a poorly paced RPG (I&amp;rsquo;m looking at you Fallout 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Players take on the role of Henry; who - for personal reasons - has volunteered as a fire watcher in the Shashone National Forest. The game hinges on the relationship between Henry and the only other character in the game, Delilah; a lookout at another tower. As the game progresses, the narrative meanders through dark themes of paranoia and vulnerability and an increasing sense of something being very wrong shrouds the player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the game ends, many of the questions surrounding the plot remain unanswered. Some people have been left very frustrated by this, but for me I found this to be one of the most interesting and intriguing aspects of Firewatch. I found myself thinking and hypothesising about the game for longer than it took me to actually complete it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, below are my theories on the game&amp;rsquo;s story arc; as posted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/Firewatch/comments/46s4pq/finished_today_heres_my_theory_of_the_main_story/&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delilah is a bit of a floozy and had a fling with Ned when he was on duty at Two Forks lookout. She shows the same behaviour with Henry; especially after drinking. She got along with Ned well enough to like him and allow him to let his son Brian stay at the tower and explore the park during his season there; but she was never in a proper relationship with Ned. If anything, she is more fond of spending time with the kid Brian than his dad.
At some point late in the season, Brian has a climbing accident whilst exploring alone and is killed. Ned instinctively searches for his missing son close to where he knows Brian has made a makeshift fort. Brian sometimes spends the whole night there, so Ned figures this is where he’ll be. After searching the area, he finds the body of his son in the cave and is devastated. He decides not to report the accident as it would put Delilah in serious trouble for knowingly allowing Brian to be in the park, at times unattended.
Instead Ned decides to tell Delilah that Brian returned to school and he too has had enough of the job and wants to leave his post, although he confesses that he doesn’t really have anywhere to go. Ned manipulates Delilah into letting him camp in the park. In return, he’ll run small errands for her like delivering her packages. Ned steals the keys to the cave and locks away the evidence of his son’s death - hoping that nobody has found the body in the interim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isolation and grief sends Ned down an unhealthy infatuation with Delilah. When Henry turns up, Ned feels jealous of the presumed ease at which Henry and Delilah can communicate through their 2-way radio. That level of access used to be privileged to him, but now he has to live in a hole in the ground; alone and unrequited. Who is this newbie? Ned loves Delilah and Henry is encroaching on what he sees as his.
Ned immediately resents Henry and wants to shake him up a bit. Being new to the stalking game, Ned is accidentally spotted by Henry on his very first evening, above the cave having just wrecked Two Peaks tower. Ned then steals some basic radio equipment from the nearby ecological station to begin monitoring the radio channel between H&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ned cuts the communications wire north of Two Peaks and frames the girls from the lake for the vandalism. This comms line is vital and so this really riles up Delilah, who asks Henry to then trash their camp. Henry seems reluctant initially over the radio, so Ned senses an opportunity to score points with Delilah. His hideout is closer to the girls’ camp than where Henry is, so he steams down there and trashes the campsite. The girls return, leave an angry note to Henry - whom they believe committed the act - and then leave. When Henry turns up at the campsite and tells Delilah he certainly didn’t do it, D knows deep down who did but she can’t come clean as she still harbours some level of loyalty to Ned. She’s also worried that if Henry finds Ned that she will get in trouble for allowing him to camp in the park.
Ned starts the ‘Flapjack’ fire (or whatever you named it in the game) in another attempt to spook and endanger Henry. He’s trying to ward him off of his beloved Delilah, but also he’s increasingly worried that Henry will find Brian’s body.
Delilah’s silence about Ned’s existence isn’t enough to stop Henry encountering Ned unexpectedly by the lake. Ned assaults Henry, but not before Henry is able to reveal to Delilah that someone has been listening to their conversations over the radio channel. D pretty much knows that this must be Ned but she doesn’t want to believe it. The seed of distrust for Ned is growing in her mind. She uses Henry as a pawn to investigate the issue further to get the proof she needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, Ned’s love for Delilah is turning sour. D’s chirpy ‘take a look at your trees poster’ message followed by the radio silence on the current channel isn’t exactly hard for Ned to work out. He simply searches the frequencies for their new channel. He feels betrayed.
He records D’s outburst about ‘burning the whole place to the ground’ and then uses Henry to relay this blackmail to D by planting the alarm clock backpack. When the alarm sounds, he knows exactly where Henry is so he knows he has time to climb the tower and pin the tape to the door. Ned gives Henry the key to the cave at this point because he is planning to murder him in cave. When Henry first visits the cave, Ned gets cold feet and tries once more to spook him by slamming the cage door. Ned is done: he can’t bring himself to kill Henry (perhaps in part because this would hurt D) so he records and plants a final recording for Henry, starts some more fires in rage, and flees.
Delilah is genuinely cut up by the news about Brian. She believes at worst that Ned murdered him and therefore she is culpable; or in the least that she is negligent by allowing Brian to be in the park in the first place. Delilah’s cowardice combined with the raging fires means she sees a way out of this without getting herself into hot water. She likes Henry but her fear of getting into trouble overrides this. She’s a screw up; an alcoholic; she has weak character. She can’t even face Henry due to her shame and guilt at the whole situation and just leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think by posting in that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/Firewatch/comments/46s4pq/finished_today_heres_my_theory_of_the_main_story/&#34;&gt;thread on Reddit&lt;/a&gt;. I go into a bit more detail about Wapati Station later on in the comments, so let me know!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve not played this game, then I encourage you to check it out or at least watch a playthrough and experience the story:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O_r6t6_bN3c&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://img.youtube.com/vi/O_r6t6_bN3c/0.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;IMAGE ALT TEXT HERE&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting to grips with illustration in Sketch</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/getting-to-grips-with-illustrations-in-sketch/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/getting-to-grips-with-illustrations-in-sketch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I&amp;rsquo;m a little late to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sketchapp.com/&#34;&gt;Sketch&lt;/a&gt; party, but I started experimenting with designing website interfaces in Sketch a few months ago. I&amp;rsquo;ve now made the complete transition - I literally uninstalled Photoshop over the Christmas break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night, I found myself experimenting with illustration in Sketch whilst watching TV and, well, ended up drawing my TV. The result is below (in SVG format; horray for vectors!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jonnykates.com/img/TV-svg.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Meta&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Responsive Column Ordering with Neat</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/responsive-column-ordering-with-neat/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/responsive-column-ordering-with-neat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://neat.bourbon.io/&#34;&gt;Neat&lt;/a&gt; by Bourbon is a nice little grid framework that bolts on to the wider Bourbon library. Neat allows you to structure your project&amp;rsquo;s layout around a fluid column based grid and then use clear semantic grid definitions in your Sass. Once you&amp;rsquo;ve defined some global variables - such as your container width, number of columns, gutter width etc. - Neat gives you a range of versatile Sass mixins that dictate an element&amp;rsquo;s layout behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if we wanted to set up a basic 12 column sidebar page layout, we might define our &lt;code&gt;aside&lt;/code&gt; element to be 3 columns wide, and our &lt;code&gt;article&lt;/code&gt; to be 9 columns wide as such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scss&#34;&gt;section {
  @include outer-container; // set this element as the 12 column container

  aside {
    @include span-columns(3); // our sidebar
  }

  article {
    @include span-columns(9); // the main body of the layout
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can then use these Neat mixins within media queries to dictate how our layout folds and wraps at different resolutions. For example, we might want both our &lt;code&gt;aside&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;article&lt;/code&gt; elements to fill the complete width of their parent container at a globally defined breakpoint, &lt;code&gt;$tablet&lt;/code&gt;. We can do this using Neat&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;fill-parent&lt;/code&gt; mixin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scss&#34;&gt;@include media($tablet) {
  aside, article {
    @include fill-parent;
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Neat &lt;em&gt;doesn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; do is let you decide what &lt;em&gt;order&lt;/em&gt; your DOM elements wrap. Flexbox gives us a couple of ways to achieve this, not least:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scss&#34;&gt;.container {
  flex-wrap: wrap-reverse;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; But Neat will always wrap from left-to-right; meaning that in our two column article/aside example, the aside will always have to wrap underneath the article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jonnykates.com/img/neat-columns.png&#34; alt=&#34;Bourbon Neat Column Ordering&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stumbled across this issue recently in a project I was working on, and soon found Github user toobulkeh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/thoughtbot/neat/issues/304&#34;&gt;issue post&lt;/a&gt; on the Neat repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that this is a limitation of Neat, but there is a bit of a hacky solution that we can implement to re-order our elements in the order we want. The trick is to order the elements in your HTML in the order you would like them to appear &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the breakpoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;container&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;aside four-cols&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    I want this div to be on the right normally, but then sit on top when the columns go full width after breakpoint
  &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;article eight-cols&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    This div is the main column and needs to sit on the left normally, but fold underneath after break
  &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, I use &lt;code&gt;float&lt;/code&gt; to force the order I want the elements to appear in &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; the breakpoint. You have to include Neat&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://thoughtbot.github.io/neat-docs/latest/#omega&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;omega&lt;/code&gt; mixin&lt;/a&gt; here to sort out the gutters as you&amp;rsquo;re using floats to botch up the column ordering that Neat expects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scss&#34;&gt;.aside {
  @include span-columns(4);
  float: right;
  @include omega;
}
.article {
  @include span-columns(8);
  float: left;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then my media query will make both &lt;code&gt;.aside&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;.article&lt;/code&gt; fill the &lt;code&gt;.container&lt;/code&gt; at my breakpoint. When this happens, the floats are basically irrelevant because they are now both set to &lt;code&gt;width: 100%&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scss&#34;&gt;.container div {
  @include media(max-width 400px) {
    @include fill-parent();
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very much a hack. We&amp;rsquo;re using CSS floats to override the expected behaviour of Neat&amp;rsquo;s column ordering. Needless to say that float shouldn&amp;rsquo;t really be used, ever. But in this scenario it does exactly what we need. If you need any help with this issue, give me a shout on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/jonnykates&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or leave a comment in that &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/thoughtbot/neat/issues/304&#34;&gt;Git issue&lt;/a&gt; and I&amp;rsquo;ll try and chime in.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My favourite albums of 2015</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/albums-of-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/albums-of-2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t tend to obsess about &amp;lsquo;albums of the year&amp;rsquo; lists as much as some, but I recently put together a list of my favourite records of 2015 for a music community, so I thought it worthwhile to share the list here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C. Duncan - Architect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everything Everything - Get To Heaven&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unknown Mortal Orchestra - Multi Love&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deerhunter - Fading Frontier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tobias Jesso Jr. - Goon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Viet Cong - Viet Cong&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tame Impala - Currents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Braids - Deep In The Iris&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Father John Misty - I Love You, Honeybear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Action Bronson - Mr. Wonderful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kurt Vile - b&amp;rsquo;lieve i&amp;rsquo;m goin down&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bersarin Quartet - III&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laura Marling - Short Movie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blur - The Magic Whip&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hey Colossus - Radio Static High&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pond - Man It Feels Like Space Again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stealing Sheep - Not Real&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John Tejada - Signs Under Test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nathan Fake - Glaive (EP)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nils Frahm - Solo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also keep a running annual Spotify playlist that has a collection of tracks that I&amp;rsquo;ve been listening to this year, regardless of the year they were recorded:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://embed.spotify.com/?uri=spotify%3Auser%3Ajkates87%3Aplaylist%3A7Lppx8W5hzgSg5zWa8JGRU&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick PMQs</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/quick-pmqs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/quick-pmqs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One weekend recently, I built a small AngularJS project that offers short, Twitter-length summaries of the back-and-forth exchanges at the weekly Prime Minister&amp;rsquo;s Questions sessions in the House of Commons. I dubbed it &amp;lsquo;Quick PMQs&amp;rsquo;, and you can check it out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quickpmqs.co.uk&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise was mostly for my own benefit, so that I could get more familiar with Angular. But I do think that in someways it raises an interesting point. Debates in the House of Commons are often conducted over a backdrop of jeering, heckling and generally antagonistic behaviour. Also, the course of the debates themselves often descends into what can only be described as a personal slagging match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair to Jeremy Corbyn, the Labour leader has tried to reset the PMQ debate; not least by inviting the public to send him questions to be put to the Prime Minister. Despite his best interests, this has had limited success - as seen in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/cloakedtruth/videos/512311918942511/?pnref=story&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quickpmqs.co.uk&#34;&gt;Quick PMQs&lt;/a&gt; can offer a brief digest of the key points at the weekly debate between JC and David Cameron.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting started with SMACSS</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/getting-started-with-SMACSS/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/getting-started-with-SMACSS/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;One of the key areas of my workflow that I have been focusing on improving in the past year or so is the organisation of my SCSS files. Frustrated with lengthy stylesheets and confusing - often repetitive - code, I decided to buy Jonathan Snook&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://shop.smacss.com/&#34;&gt;Scalable and Modular Architecture for CSS&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;; or &amp;lsquo;SMACSS&amp;rsquo; for short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introducing-smacss&#34;&gt;Introducing SMACSS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smacss.com/&#34;&gt;SMACSS&lt;/a&gt; (pronounced &amp;ldquo;smacks&amp;rdquo;) can&amp;rsquo;t really be described as a framework; there&amp;rsquo;s no library to download and its recommendations are intended as guidelines rather than rules. SMACSS is simply an approach to organising your stylesheets within a project. It tries to make managing large projects easy and logical for front end developers. SMACSS leverages SCSS&amp;rsquo;s ability to easily compile numerous partial files into a single CSS file for use in production. Snook suggests that developers shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be shy about splitting their styles into any number of &lt;code&gt;_partial.scss&lt;/code&gt; files in favour of keeping your code highly organised and modular in structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bolting on every new style onto the bottom of a single file makes finding things difficult - even with Sublime Text&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Search in project&amp;rsquo; functionality. It leads to confusion and more often than not duplication when working in collaborative teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, SMACSS is simply a way of categorising your SCSS files to avoid these pitfalls. By defining certain rules for how styles are applied in a project, everyone in your team knows the rules from the very beginning of a project. Of course, your team might already have existing rules and patterns in place; but if you don&amp;rsquo;t then SMACSS is a wonderful starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;categorisation&#34;&gt;Categorisation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are five file categories in the SMACSS approach. Here I am going to go through each category and explain what sorts of styles should be included in each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-base&#34;&gt;1. Base&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Base styles set defaults. To quote Snook directly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;[e]ssentially, a base style says that wherever this element is on the page, it should look like &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my Base folder, I tend to have a reset file, a file dedicated to typography, a file dedicated to default form styles as well as a file to store my SCSS variables. I will then also have a rather generic catch-all base file simply called &lt;code&gt;_base.scss&lt;/code&gt; that has other default styles that don&amp;rsquo;t deserve a dedicated modular sheet. For example, the &lt;code&gt;_base.scss&lt;/code&gt; partial for a project I&amp;rsquo;m currently working on has styles such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scss&#34;&gt;img {
  max-width: 100%;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-layout&#34;&gt;2. Layout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The layout folder contains all styles that control the various grids, containers and wrappers on any page. I&amp;rsquo;m currently using &lt;a href=&#34;http://bourbon.io/&#34;&gt;Bourbon&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://neat.bourbon.io/&#34;&gt;Neat&lt;/a&gt; grid framework in my projects, so I tend to install these libraries in the layout folder and then define some classes that I can extend when it comes to building the specific modules in my project. For example, I tend to always define the following classes that use Neat&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;span-columns&lt;/code&gt; mixin:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scss&#34;&gt;.one-col { @include span-columns(1); }
.two-cols { @include span-columns(2); }
.three-cols { @include span-columns(3); }
.four-cols { @include span-columns(4); }
// etc.
.full-width { @include fill-parent };
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-modules&#34;&gt;3. Modules&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the guts of your styles are built. SMACSS encourages a modular approach to front end development; a theme that is growing in popularity (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://alistapart.com/article/language-of-modular-design&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; from Alla Kholmatova). I create new partials in this folder for every different modular item that will be in use anywhere on the site. This could range from things as broad as &lt;code&gt;_header.scss&lt;/code&gt; through to a very specific block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modules folder is probably going to contain the most number of files in your SMACSS directory. When I first started using this approach, I was always very anxious about having too many modules files. However, it&amp;rsquo;s important to realise that every module needs to have its own partial: those are the rules and you should stick to them. Because one file relates to one module, then you are able to name these partials highly specifically. For example, if I have a module with the class &lt;code&gt;.callout&lt;/code&gt;, then I can create a partial called &lt;code&gt;_callout.scss&lt;/code&gt; and immediately know that this is where the styles for this class live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Snook goes into some more detail on naming rules at the bottom of &lt;a href=&#34;https://smacss.com/book/categorizing&#34;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; on the SMACSS website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-state&#34;&gt;4. State&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State rules contain styles that are specific to a particular &lt;em&gt;state&lt;/em&gt; of a module. For example, you could have a &lt;code&gt;.inactive&lt;/code&gt; state, and then define within the &lt;code&gt;_inactive.scss&lt;/code&gt; partial how your various modules should differ if this class is also applied to the element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I prefer to keep my states within a module&amp;rsquo;s partial, rather than split these out into a separate folder and files - however I can easily see how this would become unmanageable with certain types of projects that have a high level of user interaction with the interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-theme&#34;&gt;5. Theme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the theme folder is similar to the state folder and would contain various different theme styles that could be used. Again, personally I&amp;rsquo;ve never found a need for using themes, but I could see how you might want to create a few more SCSS variables files here to define different themes for your UI (for example, light or dark, high contrast etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;scratching-the-surface&#34;&gt;Scratching the surface&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This introduction is just scratching the surface of the SMACSS approach and I would highly, &lt;em&gt;highly&lt;/em&gt; recommend you &lt;a href=&#34;http://shop.smacss.com/&#34;&gt;read the book&lt;/a&gt; and encourage your team to also read the book if you&amp;rsquo;re likely to employ this approach in your workflow. Snook goes into far more detail about the organisation structure that SMACSS suggests, but also talks far more generally about the benefits of modular design as well as the importance of file organisation and the benefits that a high level of organisation can bring to a project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The responsibility of entrepreneurship over the next century</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/the-responsibility-of-entrepreneurship/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/the-responsibility-of-entrepreneurship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine one morning you get a phone call from a market research call centre. It’s a Monday and you’ve just put the kettle on, so you indulge the caller and agree to answer a quick survey. Expecting to be asked about your electricity service provider or possibly a recent purchase you made online, you’re taken aback when the caller asks bluntly, ‘On a scale of one to ten, how would you rate the state of the world today?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would you respond? There’s no denying that the problems facing our world today remain huge and urgent. They call for disruptive and decisive solutions – something that as of yet we’ve apparently been unable to crack. These problems have foiled governments, charities and philanthropists for decades. But what role can business play in righting the wrongs in society?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always been a big fan of the capabilities approach to development; first pioneered by the economist Amartya Sen in the 80’s. Sen suggested that a person’s well-being is intrinsically linked to what they are able to do. Money has traditionally been seen as the key component in enabling people but this represents a fallible (and generally westernised) approach. We’ve tried throwing money at our problems and they don’t go away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I’m excited by the growing potential of innovation to tackle society’s problems. At &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clearlyso.com&#34;&gt;ClearlySo&lt;/a&gt;, we meet entrepreneurs on a daily basis who are using their business skills to create a positive social and/or environmental impact. They don’t rely on good will and donations – they sell products and services to a market as any other private company would. This is beyond the concept of corporate social responsibility; these are private companies whose core mission is to make a positive difference as a direct result of their operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in an ever shrinking and inter-connected world, not least due to the internet. This has done two dramatic things. Firstly, it has made the access to information and education much easier – that’s a huge capability right there. Secondly, it has meant that innovators can share, influence, learn from and ultimately help those that aren’t geographically proximate to themselves. Many of the companies we work with are based in London but their direct impact is felt thousands of miles away, helping the world’s most disadvantaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jonnykates.com/img/peepoople.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Peepoople&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.peepoople.com/&#34;&gt;Peepoople&lt;/a&gt; for example, who operate in the slums of Kenya and Bangladesh turning human waste in to fertilizer – hardly a glamorous business but one which has huge impact. Single-use biodegradable toilets (known as ‘Peepoos’) are sold by female micro-entrepreneurs to citizens of the slum who then drop their deposits at a local collection points in exchange for a refund. The collected waste is then transported to a storage area where it is transformed in to useable fertiliser, which can then be sold back to the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The women who sell the Peepoos receive business training as well as tuition on how to promote hygiene to the customers they meet. Aside from providing a valuable fertiliser to a subsistent community, Peepoople are also tackling a larger issue of water contamination in some of the poorest slums on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the growth rate of social enterprises, at least from what we see in the UK, is staggering. ClearlySo helps social entrepreneurs to raise equity investments of at least £300k, and we are inundated with businesses to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You would be forgiven for offering the market researcher cold-caller a fairly modest score in response to their question ‘how would you rate the state of the world today?’ But when asked where we’ll be in 100 years, the most stringent pessimist within me can’t help but believe social enterprises will have played a substantial role in raising the score.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Circular Economy</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/the-circular-economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/the-circular-economy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &amp;lsquo;Circular Economy&amp;rsquo; is an idea that has its founding in the 1970s but has only recently seen a real resurgence in popularity - not least due to the efforts of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ellenmacarthurfoundation.org/&#34;&gt;Ellen MacArthur Foundation&lt;/a&gt;; an independent charity established by the well-known solo long-distance yachtswoman Ellen MacArthur in 2010, which has emerged as one of the leading authorities on this approach to sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the theory of a Circular Economy doing the rounds (pun certainly intended) within the sustainability discourse, I admit it was a fairly new concept to me. So I decided to do a bit of research and write up this quick dummies guide to the Circular Economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our natural world is reliant on many &amp;lsquo;closed-loop&amp;rsquo; systems; the water cycle being a prime example. In this system, nothing is created and nothing is lost. Rain falls on the ground  which flows in to rivers, which flows in to the sea and is eventually returned to the atmosphere where the cycle begins again. The Circular Economy argues that our models of manufacturing and consumption could benefit from adopting similar principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently had to replace my washing machine. As an environmentally conscientious 21st Century &amp;lsquo;global citizen&amp;rsquo;, a pang of unassailable horror washes over me whenever I have to commit something to landfill. Despite my pleas, the plumber assured me that the machine was categorically kaput and whilst certain components may be reclaimed by the disposal handler, not an insignificant amount of this hunk of &amp;lsquo;broken&amp;rsquo; metal was going to wind up in a hole somewhere for the next however-many-hundreds-of-years. But hey; that&amp;rsquo;s normal right? It can&amp;rsquo;t be helped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine a system where rather than consuming products, we paid for &lt;em&gt;services&lt;/em&gt;. For example, imagine the washing machine was the property of its manufacturer. As an end user, I am simply leasing the use of the machine on a fixed term basis or whenever I want to wash my clothes on an &amp;lsquo;on-demand&amp;rsquo; basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly the buck of responsibility has passed from consumer to designer. The upkeep and quality of the product becomes not only the responsibility of the manufacturer, but it&amp;rsquo;s in their economic interest to optimise it. The system has become &lt;em&gt;performance based&lt;/em&gt;. The parts and labour that go in to making a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; washing machine to replace a broken unit become an internalised cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that right from the drawing board, products are designed to last as long as possible. High quality individual components are up-cycled as product lines are upgraded. (What&amp;rsquo;s happening to all those supposedly precious metals in our current electronic devices?). Premature obsolescence would be phased out rather than designed in; as the following video from the aforementioned Ellen Macarthur Foundation superbly points out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Cd_isKtGaf8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what&amp;rsquo;s standing in the way of a Circular Economy? One of the biggest problems to scaling up is undoubtedly practicality: how do we &lt;em&gt;practically&lt;/em&gt; get manufacturers to redesign their products and services from scratch? In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/sustainable-business/video/knowledge-need-driving-interest-circular-economy-video&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;, Ian Cheshire - chief executive of Kingfisher estimates that their turn around from product design to point of sale is about 18 months. Even if a Circular Economy became the &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; economic model overnight, there&amp;rsquo;s still an element of patience involved when turning around a ship of this size. He does - however - suggest that low economic activity could present the Circular Economy with an opportunity to grow quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing that could help get this idea moving is by encouraging customers to vote with their wallets. As more and more industries begin to experiment with the service model, there&amp;rsquo;s room for us to reward the bold steps taken towards a closed-loop system. By putting pressure on the marketers - the people driving brand desire and needs - the Circular Economy could quickly become the next buzz term amidst modern sustainable consumers (if it isn&amp;rsquo;t already).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I began to learn more about the Circular Economy, the more it struck me as an obvious and achievable sustainability solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact  my first reaction was that this revolutionary process has &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; happened in the film and music industry. Services like Spotify and Netflix allow consumers to stream (i.e. lease) media on a pay-as-you-go or fixed basis. I for one have bought my last DVD and I&amp;rsquo;m not alone. The service solution even flies in the face of media piracy, which was in turn a knee-jerk reaction to a redundant economic model. It&amp;rsquo;s now easier to legitimately rent media rather than steal it; although the comparisons to other industries dry up a bit with this point (I&amp;rsquo;m unlikely to lug home a stolen washing machine).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless  the service model seems to make sense and is compatible with our modern consumer habits. I&amp;rsquo;m excited by the prospects of a Circular Economy - it appears like a practical way of internalising the negative externalities of manufacturing through economic incentives rather than punitive sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>