<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Personal on Jonny Kates</title>
    <link>http://jonnykates.com/tags/personal/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Personal on Jonny Kates</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://jonnykates.com/tags/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Ch-ch-ch-ch-changes</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/ch-ch-ch-ch-changes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/ch-ch-ch-ch-changes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It feels like I&amp;rsquo;m on the cusp of a few major life changes. Next year, I&amp;rsquo;ll be getting married; moving house; and turning 30 - all possibly within a month of each other. In an attempt to minimise the risk of any potential mental breakdown, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to make some changes in my professional life today to put me in a better position to make these significant life changes (namely moving house) tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started working on a freelance basis as a designer and frontend developer for an organisation called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.raisingit.com/&#34;&gt;Raising IT&lt;/a&gt;. The work is mostly remote, meaning that Natalie and I can look at getting on the property ladder somewhere that isn&amp;rsquo;t the south east of England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first became aware of Raising IT some years ago whilst working at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.clearlyso.com/&#34;&gt;ClearlySo&lt;/a&gt; and have followed their progress ever since. They have developed a website platform and CMS that is specifically tailored to the needs of non-profits. Features such as fundraising and social media integration are part of the platform out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where Raising IT really provide value though, is in the work they do with clients on their online strategy. Before any designs or any code is touched, clients complete a two day strategy workshop to hash out all of the many suggestions and ideas that are an inevitable part of any purpose driven organisation with numerous stakeholders. Before I sit with the client in a design capacity, these brainstorm discussions have already been tackled meaning that a lot of the heavy lifting in terms of defining the direction of the website have been nailed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who often works on projects from cover to cover in a project management capacity, this process is great from a designer&amp;rsquo;s perspective as it means the design process can be incredibly focused over a relatively short sprint. Two weeks in fact - from kicking off the design to having a fully signed off, built, and tested site template into which the client can populate their content. If you don&amp;rsquo;t distract designers from the design, they can produce results incredibly fast. Other efficiencies are baked into the development process as well - such as a starting SCSS framework that has been specifically tailored to Raising IT&amp;rsquo;s platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also great to be working with some clients who are doing incredible things; which is something I have missed in the past couple of years. I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to getting stuck into a new challenge and edging closer to full-time freelance work (if you hate your current website, hit me up!). Here&amp;rsquo;s to a busy 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My favourite albums of 2015</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/albums-of-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/albums-of-2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t tend to obsess about &amp;lsquo;albums of the year&amp;rsquo; lists as much as some, but I recently put together a list of my favourite records of 2015 for a music community, so I thought it worthwhile to share the list here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C. Duncan - Architect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everything Everything - Get To Heaven&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unknown Mortal Orchestra - Multi Love&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deerhunter - Fading Frontier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tobias Jesso Jr. - Goon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Viet Cong - Viet Cong&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tame Impala - Currents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Braids - Deep In The Iris&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Father John Misty - I Love You, Honeybear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Action Bronson - Mr. Wonderful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kurt Vile - b&amp;rsquo;lieve i&amp;rsquo;m goin down&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bersarin Quartet - III&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laura Marling - Short Movie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blur - The Magic Whip&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hey Colossus - Radio Static High&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pond - Man It Feels Like Space Again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stealing Sheep - Not Real&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John Tejada - Signs Under Test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nathan Fake - Glaive (EP)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nils Frahm - Solo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also keep a running annual Spotify playlist that has a collection of tracks that I&amp;rsquo;ve been listening to this year, regardless of the year they were recorded:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://embed.spotify.com/?uri=spotify%3Auser%3Ajkates87%3Aplaylist%3A7Lppx8W5hzgSg5zWa8JGRU&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>