<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social Enterprise on Jonny Kates</title>
    <link>http://jonnykates.com/tags/social-enterprise/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Social Enterprise on Jonny Kates</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://jonnykates.com/tags/social-enterprise/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The responsibility of entrepreneurship over the next century</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/the-responsibility-of-entrepreneurship/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/the-responsibility-of-entrepreneurship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine one morning you get a phone call from a market research call centre. It’s a Monday and you’ve just put the kettle on, so you indulge the caller and agree to answer a quick survey. Expecting to be asked about your electricity service provider or possibly a recent purchase you made online, you’re taken aback when the caller asks bluntly, ‘On a scale of one to ten, how would you rate the state of the world today?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would you respond? There’s no denying that the problems facing our world today remain huge and urgent. They call for disruptive and decisive solutions – something that as of yet we’ve apparently been unable to crack. These problems have foiled governments, charities and philanthropists for decades. But what role can business play in righting the wrongs in society?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always been a big fan of the capabilities approach to development; first pioneered by the economist Amartya Sen in the 80’s. Sen suggested that a person’s well-being is intrinsically linked to what they are able to do. Money has traditionally been seen as the key component in enabling people but this represents a fallible (and generally westernised) approach. We’ve tried throwing money at our problems and they don’t go away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I’m excited by the growing potential of innovation to tackle society’s problems. At &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clearlyso.com&#34;&gt;ClearlySo&lt;/a&gt;, we meet entrepreneurs on a daily basis who are using their business skills to create a positive social and/or environmental impact. They don’t rely on good will and donations – they sell products and services to a market as any other private company would. This is beyond the concept of corporate social responsibility; these are private companies whose core mission is to make a positive difference as a direct result of their operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in an ever shrinking and inter-connected world, not least due to the internet. This has done two dramatic things. Firstly, it has made the access to information and education much easier – that’s a huge capability right there. Secondly, it has meant that innovators can share, influence, learn from and ultimately help those that aren’t geographically proximate to themselves. Many of the companies we work with are based in London but their direct impact is felt thousands of miles away, helping the world’s most disadvantaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://jonnykates.com/img/peepoople.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Peepoople&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.peepoople.com/&#34;&gt;Peepoople&lt;/a&gt; for example, who operate in the slums of Kenya and Bangladesh turning human waste in to fertilizer – hardly a glamorous business but one which has huge impact. Single-use biodegradable toilets (known as ‘Peepoos’) are sold by female micro-entrepreneurs to citizens of the slum who then drop their deposits at a local collection points in exchange for a refund. The collected waste is then transported to a storage area where it is transformed in to useable fertiliser, which can then be sold back to the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The women who sell the Peepoos receive business training as well as tuition on how to promote hygiene to the customers they meet. Aside from providing a valuable fertiliser to a subsistent community, Peepoople are also tackling a larger issue of water contamination in some of the poorest slums on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the growth rate of social enterprises, at least from what we see in the UK, is staggering. ClearlySo helps social entrepreneurs to raise equity investments of at least £300k, and we are inundated with businesses to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You would be forgiven for offering the market researcher cold-caller a fairly modest score in response to their question ‘how would you rate the state of the world today?’ But when asked where we’ll be in 100 years, the most stringent pessimist within me can’t help but believe social enterprises will have played a substantial role in raising the score.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Circular Economy</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/the-circular-economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/the-circular-economy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &amp;lsquo;Circular Economy&amp;rsquo; is an idea that has its founding in the 1970s but has only recently seen a real resurgence in popularity - not least due to the efforts of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ellenmacarthurfoundation.org/&#34;&gt;Ellen MacArthur Foundation&lt;/a&gt;; an independent charity established by the well-known solo long-distance yachtswoman Ellen MacArthur in 2010, which has emerged as one of the leading authorities on this approach to sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the theory of a Circular Economy doing the rounds (pun certainly intended) within the sustainability discourse, I admit it was a fairly new concept to me. So I decided to do a bit of research and write up this quick dummies guide to the Circular Economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our natural world is reliant on many &amp;lsquo;closed-loop&amp;rsquo; systems; the water cycle being a prime example. In this system, nothing is created and nothing is lost. Rain falls on the ground  which flows in to rivers, which flows in to the sea and is eventually returned to the atmosphere where the cycle begins again. The Circular Economy argues that our models of manufacturing and consumption could benefit from adopting similar principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently had to replace my washing machine. As an environmentally conscientious 21st Century &amp;lsquo;global citizen&amp;rsquo;, a pang of unassailable horror washes over me whenever I have to commit something to landfill. Despite my pleas, the plumber assured me that the machine was categorically kaput and whilst certain components may be reclaimed by the disposal handler, not an insignificant amount of this hunk of &amp;lsquo;broken&amp;rsquo; metal was going to wind up in a hole somewhere for the next however-many-hundreds-of-years. But hey; that&amp;rsquo;s normal right? It can&amp;rsquo;t be helped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine a system where rather than consuming products, we paid for &lt;em&gt;services&lt;/em&gt;. For example, imagine the washing machine was the property of its manufacturer. As an end user, I am simply leasing the use of the machine on a fixed term basis or whenever I want to wash my clothes on an &amp;lsquo;on-demand&amp;rsquo; basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly the buck of responsibility has passed from consumer to designer. The upkeep and quality of the product becomes not only the responsibility of the manufacturer, but it&amp;rsquo;s in their economic interest to optimise it. The system has become &lt;em&gt;performance based&lt;/em&gt;. The parts and labour that go in to making a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; washing machine to replace a broken unit become an internalised cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that right from the drawing board, products are designed to last as long as possible. High quality individual components are up-cycled as product lines are upgraded. (What&amp;rsquo;s happening to all those supposedly precious metals in our current electronic devices?). Premature obsolescence would be phased out rather than designed in; as the following video from the aforementioned Ellen Macarthur Foundation superbly points out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Cd_isKtGaf8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what&amp;rsquo;s standing in the way of a Circular Economy? One of the biggest problems to scaling up is undoubtedly practicality: how do we &lt;em&gt;practically&lt;/em&gt; get manufacturers to redesign their products and services from scratch? In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/sustainable-business/video/knowledge-need-driving-interest-circular-economy-video&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;, Ian Cheshire - chief executive of Kingfisher estimates that their turn around from product design to point of sale is about 18 months. Even if a Circular Economy became the &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; economic model overnight, there&amp;rsquo;s still an element of patience involved when turning around a ship of this size. He does - however - suggest that low economic activity could present the Circular Economy with an opportunity to grow quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing that could help get this idea moving is by encouraging customers to vote with their wallets. As more and more industries begin to experiment with the service model, there&amp;rsquo;s room for us to reward the bold steps taken towards a closed-loop system. By putting pressure on the marketers - the people driving brand desire and needs - the Circular Economy could quickly become the next buzz term amidst modern sustainable consumers (if it isn&amp;rsquo;t already).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I began to learn more about the Circular Economy, the more it struck me as an obvious and achievable sustainability solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact  my first reaction was that this revolutionary process has &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; happened in the film and music industry. Services like Spotify and Netflix allow consumers to stream (i.e. lease) media on a pay-as-you-go or fixed basis. I for one have bought my last DVD and I&amp;rsquo;m not alone. The service solution even flies in the face of media piracy, which was in turn a knee-jerk reaction to a redundant economic model. It&amp;rsquo;s now easier to legitimately rent media rather than steal it; although the comparisons to other industries dry up a bit with this point (I&amp;rsquo;m unlikely to lug home a stolen washing machine).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless  the service model seems to make sense and is compatible with our modern consumer habits. I&amp;rsquo;m excited by the prospects of a Circular Economy - it appears like a practical way of internalising the negative externalities of manufacturing through economic incentives rather than punitive sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>