<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>General Election 2017 on Jonny Kates</title>
    <link>http://jonnykates.com/tags/general-election-2017/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in General Election 2017 on Jonny Kates</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://jonnykates.com/tags/general-election-2017/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How the left can win</title>
      <link>http://jonnykates.com/blog/how-the-left-can-win/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2017 12:13:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonnykates.com/blog/how-the-left-can-win/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, Theresa May has fired the starting gun this week on a snap general election in 7 weeks time. An election that she is determined to be focused on Brexit, with a core tenet of her platform being simply that destabalising the government at this point will jeapordise a successful Brexit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And whilst Brexit will clearly (and rightly) play an important factor in the vote, it&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that this is still a general election; not a rerun of last year&amp;rsquo;s referendum. The winner of which will have the responsibility of leading the &lt;em&gt;whole&lt;/em&gt; country over the next five years. Clearly that role is going to involve far more than just taking Britain out of the European Union; and actually that presents the left with a golden opportunity to put an end to this Tory government which is at risk of damaging our public services beyond repair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already, however, this feels like a very different election - not just because of the Brexit undertones and the surprise nature in which it was announced. Opinion polls seem to be predicting an irrevocable lead for the Conservatives; highlighting ongoing divisions amongst the Labour Party over its leadership and direction. Yet the opportunity for the left here is very real and I believe has been underestimated by the Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three things that need to happen over the next 7 weeks for the left to take advantage of this election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, Labour need to fully get behind Jeremy Corbyn&amp;rsquo;s campaign. Corbyn supporters have been saying as such since he was first elected to the leadership position, however that unity seems to have failed to materialise within the PLP let alone the wider supporter base. But with a general election round the corner, there simply isn&amp;rsquo;t time for the nay-sayers to derail Corbyn so it&amp;rsquo;s somewhat illogical to diminish his leadership over the next couple of months. Bury the hatchet and recognise that Labour is going to have to play a primary role in ousting this government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they can&amp;rsquo;t do it alone. Even the most skeptical poll critic has to acknowledge that it looks impossible that Labour could win a majority in a matter of weeks. Instead, the left needs to rally &lt;strong&gt;together&lt;/strong&gt; against the Tories as a means to an end. A progressive coalition is the best outcome for Labour, Lib Dems, Greens and the SNP. Collaborating on targeting winnable seats to avoid too many head-to-heads within the left could be vital - especially with the SNP&amp;rsquo;s role in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly the left-leaning amongst the electorate need to collaborate to tip the balance in our favour. Corbyn claimed this week that the political system is &amp;lsquo;rigged&amp;rsquo; in favour of those who protect and represent the elite. If the game is rigged, you have to cheat. Strategic voting amongst the left could again help to topple Tory seats. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen initiatives that help to organise tactical voting in the past, but it feels like this is going to have to play an integral role if we want a left coalition come June 8th. Gina Miller - the pro-EU campaigner who legally challenged the government over parliamentary voting for Article 50 - has set up a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gofundme.com/whats-best-for-britain&#34;&gt;crowdfunding campaign&lt;/a&gt; to finance candidates who specifically back an open vote on Brexit terms. Whilst this feels a little &amp;lsquo;single-policy&amp;rsquo; focused - which I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned I think we need to avoid - it&amp;rsquo;s an interesting initiative that highlights the need for taking on this election strategically.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>